lor A. **Howell**

Durand 032, Stanford, CA 94305 USA

【(+1) 801 · 300 · 9431 | ■ thowell@stanford.edu | 😭 thowell.github.io | 🖸 thowell



Summary_

Currently, I am a Ph.D. candidate at Stanford University. I work on optimization-based tools for simulation, planning, and control for robotic systems. My expertise include: numerical optimization, technical computing, automatic control, and modeling of dynamical systems.

Education

Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

PH.D. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Sept. 2017 - Dec. 2022 (expected)

- · Optimization, Control, Robotics
- · Advisors: Zachary Manchester, Allison Okamura

Stanford University

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

· Automatic Controls, Robotics

Stanford, CA, USA Sept. 2017 - June. 2019

University of Utah

B.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

- Summa Cum Laude
- Capstone Project: Wireless Power for Aerial Robots

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

May 2013 - Dec. 2016

Research_

Robotic Exploration Lab, Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

May 2018 - present

My research is focused on developing optimization-based tools for simulation, planning, and control of robotic systems. Currently, I am working on algorithms for fast model-predictive control, solvers for non-convex planning problems, and differentiable physics engines.

Telerobotics Laboratory, University of Utah

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Oct. 2015 - Dec. 2016

I devised and implemented a control scheme to sort swarms of microrobots using rotating uniform magnetic fields for minimally invasive medical applications. This work included: applied physics, simulation, nonlinear optimization, fabrication of a scaled microrobot swarm, and writing C++ code to control a tri-axial Helmholtz-coil system.

Utah Center of Excellence for Biomedical Microfluidics, University of Utah

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sept. 2014 - Oct. 2015

I designed and built a forty-eight-syringe pump for a medical microfluidic system, developed standard operating procedures for a highthroughput drug screening and cytotoxicity evaluation system, and performed statistical analysis for ovarian-cancer cell experiments.

Experience ___

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

DeepMind

London, United Kingdom

June. 2022 - Sept. 2022

· MuJoCo simulation team

San Francisco, CA, USA (remote)

Google Brain

RESEARCH INTERN

differentiable optimization-based dynamics for trajectory optimization

· contributed to open-source JAX project: trajax

June. 2021 - Sept. 2021

Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics, Stanford University

Stanford, CA, USA

COURSE ASSISTANT - DYNAMICS AND CONTROL OF AIRCRAFT (AA271A)

Apr. 2021 - Jun. 2021

- · held office hours four times per week
- graded assignments and exams

INSTRUCTOR - GREAT SUMMER CAMP Jun. 2017 - Jul. 2017

- · led a teaching team of three
- taught practical robotics and programming skills to elementary school students using the LEGO Mindstorm platform
- developed projects and challenges for FLL skills, telerobotics, and kinetic-art themed weeks

Cornaby-Howell LLC Salt Lake City, UT, USA

CO-FOUNDER, ENGINEER

FRONT DESK CLERK

Apr. 2015 - Oct. 2015

Apr. 2013 - Aug. 2013

Aug. 2007 - Jan. 2011

- prototyped systems: touch-display module with GUI, Arduino C code, a lead-screw system, and syringe attachment modules for precision highthroughput syringe pumps
- · designed hardware schematics for patent application

Ramada Limited Draper Draper, UT, USA

- · manager on duty: checked in and out guests, made reservations, and ran breakfast
- developed communication and practical problem solving skills

Designer Draper, UT, USA

TWISTY PUZZLES

- designed and built twisty puzzles with selling prices ranging from \$25 \$850
- exhibited my work at the community's premier international event: Dutch Cube Day 2008

Publications

CALIPSO: A Differentiable Solver for Trajectory Optimization with Conic and Complementarity 2022 Constraints, T. Howell, K. Tracy, S. Le Cleac'h. ISRR 2022.

Dojo: A Differentiable Physics Engine for Robotics, T. Howell*, S. Le Cleac'h*, Z. Kolter, M. Schwager, Z. Manchester. (arXiv).

Trajectory Optimization with Optimization-Based Dynamics, T. Howell, S. Le Cleac'h, S. Singh, P. 2021 Florence, Z. Manchester, V. Sindhwani. ICRA 2022.

Fast Contact-Implicit Model-Predictive Control, S. Le Cleac'h*, T. Howell*, M. Schwager, Z. Manchester. (arXiv).

Direct Policy Optimization using Deterministic Sampling and Collocation, T. Howell, C. Fu, Z.

Manchester. Robotics and Automation Letters.

Scalable Cooperative Transport of Cable-Suspended Loads with UAVs using Distributed Trajectory

- 2020 Optimization, B. Jackson*, T. Howell*, K. Shah, M. Schwager, Z. Manchester. Robotics and Automation Letters.
- ALTRO: A Fast Solver for Constrained Trajectory Optimization, T. Howell*, B. Jackson*, Z. Manchester. 2019 International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems. Macao, China.
- Sorting Rotating Micromachines By Variations in Their Magnetic Properties, T. Howell, B. Osting, J. 2018 Abbott. Physical Review Applied.
- Use of a highly parallel Microfluidic Flow Cell Array to determine therapeutic drug dose response 2017 curves, J. Arellano, T. Howell, J. Gammon, S. Cho, M. Janat Amsbury, B. Gale. Biomedical Microdevices.

Skills

Programming Julia, C/C++, Python

Computational MFX, Git, Linux, SNOPT, Ipopt, CVX/Convex.jl, MeshCat, MuJoCo, JAX, Solidworks, VSCode, Arduino **Fabrication** Mill, Lathe, Vacuum Forming, Laser Cutting, Mold Making and Casting, Metal Sheet Fabrication

Community Outreach

Co-organizer, of Social Impact Night event at Stanford University to connect social-impact focused students 2019 and entrepreneurs

Mentor, to three summer interns at the Telerobotics Laboratory and developed soft robots with potential as catheter tips that will increase insertion distance deep in the brain and other hard-to-reach locations in the

Science-fair Judge, for local elementary school to provide feedback to students about their projects 2015

Fellowships & Scholarships _____

Stanford Graduate Fellowship (2017 – 2018) · University of Utah Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program Fellowship (2016) · The Boeing Company Scholarship (2016) · Shirley L. & Kathelyne O. Evans Endowed Scholarship (2016) · Big Ten+ Grad Expo Travel Scholarship (2016) · University of Utah Presidential Scholarship (2013 – 2016)

Coursework_

Convex Optimization · Optimal Control · Nonlinear Control · Advanced Software Development · Engineering Design Optimization · Deep Learning · State Estimation · Principles of Robotic Autonomy · Introduction to Mechatronics · Linear Dynamical Systems · Introduction to Robotics · Machine Learning · Decision Making Under Uncertainty · Control Design Techniques · Advanced Robotic Manipulation · Advanced Feedback Control · Introduction to Optimization · Experimental Robotics · Multi-robot Systems · State Space Control · Design of Experiments · Introduction to Finite Element Method · Programming for Engineers · RL for Stochastic Control in Finance